RG 103, Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company
Connecticut State Library
- Legal File, circa 1831-1943; T001481; 6.50 cubic feet
  - Series 4. Patents, circa 1831-1943
    - Applications, 1844-1856; 6 folders (Box 45)
      - 1856 (Box 45)
    - Assignments, 1836-1910; 7 folders (Box 45)
      Contains information on the transfer or purchase of patent rights from the original holder to Sam Colt or the Colt Company. Accompanying correspondence and actual agreement are in the files.
      Arranged chronologcally by date of transfer agreement. Item listing in first folder.
      - 1836 (Box 45)
      - 1850 (Box 45)
      - 1871 (Box 45)
      - 1872 (Box 45)
      - 1880-1881 (Box 45)
      - 1884 (Box 45)
      - 1893 (Box 45)
      - 1910 (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, 1835-1894; 15 folders (Box 45)
      Contains mostly incoming letters from patent attorneys concerning pending patent applications and possible infringements. Most of this correspondence is from John E. Earle, a New Haven patent attorney. Also contains letters requesting Colt Company support for adoption of a new invention.
      Arranged chronologically by date of creation. Item listing in first folder.
      - 1835-1856 (Box 45)
      - 1873-1919 (Box 45)
      - 1878 (Box 45)
      - 1880-1888 (Box 45)
      - 1881 (Box 45)
      - 1881, 1884 (Box 45)
      - 1884-1887 (Box 45)
      - 1885-1887 (Box 45)
      - 1886, 2 folders (Box 45)
      - 1882-1889 (Box 45)
      - 1884-1886 (Box 45)
      - 1892 (Box 45)
      - 1893-1895 (Box 45)
      - 1894 (Box 45)
    - Extensions, 1840-1871; 7 folders (Box 46)
      Contains applications for and accompanying documentation for an extension for an existing patent at the time of expiration. Also contains Congressional reports on Samuel Colt's 1848-1849 and 1857 patent extension cases.
      Arranged chronologically by date of extension application. Item listing in first folder.
      - 1848 (Box 46)
      - 1840-1851 (Box 46)
      - 1855 (Box 46)
      - 1858, 3 folders (Box 46)
      - 1871 (Box 46)
    - Interferences/Infringements, 1859-1903; 14 folders (Box 46)
      Contains claims and opinions concerning cases of patent interference relating to the Colt Company, its contractors or employees.
      Arranged in chronological order. Item listing in first folder.
      - 1859 (Box 46)
      - 1869 (Box 46)
      - 1872 (Box 46)
      - 1882 (Box 46)
      - 1884, 4 folders (Box 46)
      - 1885, 2 folders (Box 46)
      - 1888 (Box 46)
      - 1893 (Box 46)
      - 1892, 1896 (Box 46)
      - 1903 (Box 46)
    - Licenses, 1870-1889; 3 folders (Box 46)
      Licenses were issued to the Colt Company granting it the right to manufacture, sell and use an invention without fear of patent infringement.
      Arranged in chronological order with an item listing in the first folder.
      - 1870 (Box 46)
      - 1872 (Box 46)
      - 1889 (Box 46)
    - Lists, 1890-1907; 5 folders (Box 46)
      Lists were compiled by the Colt Company or the individual inventor on the patents held by each.
      Contains lists of patents held by the Gatling Gun Company, Fabrique Nationale/John Browning and patents assigned to E.K. Root.
      In chronological order with an item listing in the first folder.
      - circa 1890 (Box 46)
      - 1898 (Box 46)
      - 1907 (Box 46)
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 46)
    - Opinions, 1867-1943; 9 folders (Box 47)
      Patent opinions were issued in the form of correspondence by patent attorneys and concerned whether new patent application posed any problems.
      Arranged in chronological order by date of correspondence. See item listing in first folder.
      - 1867 (Box 47)
      - 1874 (Box 47)
      - 1877 (Box 47)
      - 1880 (Box 47)
      - 1884 (Box 47)
      - 1886 (Box 47)
      - 1901 July, October (Box 47)
      - 1901 August (Box 47)
      - 1943 (Box 47)
    - Specifications, 1836-1920 (Box 48-53)
      Patent specifications detail the design elements of the new invention and generally include the drawings. Also contains patent specifications presented to numerous countries, including Austria, France, Germany, Great Britain and Italy, with most presented to the United States. Naturally, because of the number of foreign countries represented, a number of patent specifications are in a foreign language. No translations made. Additional design drawings in oversize box 53A. Patent specifications contain information on the invention, the inventor, the date, and the country the patent was requested form. Some handwritten, some typewritten. Contains Patent Gazette reprints and photostats.
      Arranged by number assigned by patent office. Includes four itemized lists arranged by patent number, chronological by date, alphabetical by country, and alphabetical by inventor.
      A detailed listing is available at the History and Genealogy reference desk.
    - Drawings, circa 1831-1859 (Box 53A oversize)
  - Series 5. Power of Attorney, 1849-1894; 3 folders
    Contains handwritten copies of the power of attorney granted to Elisha Colt by Samuel Colt, 1849, correspondence concerning a power of attorney granted to J.D. Greene by V.A. King, and the power of attorney granted to Mexican agent A.E. Combaluzier by the Colt Company.
    Arranged in chronological order. See item list in first folder.
    - 1849 October 13 (Box 53)
    - 1884 July 8 (Box 53)
    - 1894 November 10 (Box 53)
  - Miscellaneous, 1856, 1885; 2 folders
- Administrative File, circa 1836-1980; T001481; 9 cubic feet
  - Diaries, 1865-1925
    Evidence suggests that company administrators or prominent employees created these items. The contents of this series varies: Records of daily appointments and other notes by company officials; notes on patents, and engineering and mathematical computations, enclosures of articles from American Machinist, and notes of excavation work in South Meadows from 1895-1906.
    Arranged by date of entry. W.B. Franklin's diary is indexed in the Index to Correspondence in this File. There is also an index to a diary not included in this record group, dated January-March 1871. No index for other items.
    - Daily Appointment Journals (handwritten with enclosures), 1893, 1902, 1905, 1908-1911; 4 volumes (bound) (Box 54)
    - Diaries (handwritten), 2 diaries (bound) (Box 54)
      - W.B. Franklin, 1865-1867 (Box 54)
        Franklin was Vice President and General Agent, 1866-1888.
      - S. Stone, 1925 (Box 54)
        Stone was President, 1921-1944.
    - Personal Notebooks, 1883-1910 (Box 54)
      - C.J. Ehbets, 1883-1910; 6 volumes (bound) + enclosures. (Box 54)
        Ehbets was patent attorney.
        RESTRICTED
        The notebooks are in very fragile condition. A use copy is available in the box for researchers to use.
        Includes information on various patents, mathematical notes, and a sketchbook of fellow administrators, 1872.
    - Stenographer's Notebooks, 4 notepads (Box 54)
      Dictation not transcribed.
      - 1901 January 21-1901 January 30 (Box 54)
      - 1901 January 31-1901 February 11 (Box 54)
      - 1901 February 11-1901 February 22 (Box 54)
      - 1901 October 18-1901 October 26 (Box 54)
  - Company History, circa 1846-1979
    - Biographies (printed, typed and handwritten), 2 folders (Box 55)
      Evidence suggest that the biographical files on the individuals that comprised the company were kept on record for public use.
      - Internal, Employees and Inventors (available for publication) (Box 55)
        J. Browning, M. Bulkeley, B.F. Conner, W.B. Franklin, R.J. Gatling, R.W.H. Jarvis, W. Mason, C.L.F. Robinson, E.K. Root, W.C. Skinner, S.M. Stone, A.L. Ulrich. Also, 1890 award presented to C.J. Ehbets by Franklin Institute.
      - Samuel Colt, 1814-1862; 1 folder (Box 55)
        Includes September 1, 1853 certificate from C.H. Pond presenting S. Colt as Major Commandant; copy of 1855 speech given at the Institute of Civil Engineers; newspaper clippings and obituary notices; coat-of-arms; Colt family tree; items on murder trial of brother, John Colt; and 1914 articles on celebration of 100th anniversary of Colt's birth (photostat).
    - Histories (handwritten and typed), 2 folders (Box 55)
      Evidence suggest that the historical files on the company were kept on record for public use.
      - Internal (Box 55)
        Synopsis of arms manufactured over the years, 1830-1916; draft of Arms Production, 1838-1911 (see Records of Colt Company production for bound copy, 1838-1949); Development of Colt Revolver; Development of Machine Guns, 1862-1943; and papers on the Colt-Walker revolver, 1846-1847 correspondence (photocopies) pertaining to the contract with United States Government; (typed) copies of correspondence and photos of letters of S. Walker and S. Colt from same 1846-1847 period. Originals of these photos were loaned to Colt's by Walker's daughter in 1939.
      - External (Box 55)
        Items written about the Colt Company and its history.
        (Also see: Printed Materials/Periodicals).
    - Obituary Notices (Box 55)
      Consists of press releases, newspaper clippings and official announcements by the company related to employees and Hartford notables.
    - Scrapbooks (bound and unbound) (Box 56)
      Created by the Colt Company Museum staff. Generally contains programs of miscellaneous United States events or celebrations, Christmas cards, employee obituary clippings, and shareholder's reports. Two scrapbooks contain samples of Colt Company stationery, including blank letterheads, envelopes, shipping labels and business cards.
      Arranged internally by date of event or article. No index.
      - 1850-1860 (Box 56)
      - 1877-1878 (Box 56)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 56)
      - 1900-1929 (Box 56)
      - 1930-1931 (Box 56)
      - 1932-1933, 2 folders (Box 56)
      - 1934 (Box 57)
      - 1935 (Box 57)
      - Labor strike, 1935; 2 items (Box 57)
      - Arms probe, 1934 (Box 58)
      - Arms probe, 1936 (Box 58)
      - Flood, 1936; 2 folders (Box 58)
      - 1937-1938, 2 folders (Box 58)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 59)
      - Colt's Hobby Shows, 1935-1939 (Box 59)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 59)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 59)
      - 1941 (Box 60)
      - 1942-1943 (Box 60)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 60)
      - 1944-1947 (Box 60)
      - 1949-1956 (Box 60)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 60)
    - Stationery, circa 1850-1979; 1 folder (Box 61)
      Includes blank letterheads, envelopes, shipping labels, and business cards. Also, 6 stickers of the Seth Parker's Singing School, 1929 (sponsored by Colt's), 2 impressions of Company seal, a blank Colt Company check, and 13 blank sheets of Inspector of Factories, E. Burrows Brown letterhead.
  - In-House Communications, 1938-1971
    Many of these items are between administrators at the Firearms Division and Colt Industries, NYC.
    Arranged chronologically by date written or posted. No index.
    - In-house notices (plant publicity), 1938-1942 (Box 61)
    - Inter-office correspondence, 1938, 1940, 1942, 1969-1971 (Box 61)
      Contains correspondence between Hartford administration and Colt Industris, NYC. Also, telephone directory, 1969.
  - Records of the Colt Company Museum, 1887-1957
    Contains assorted items used in the Museum and saved by staff members.
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 61)
      - Inventory of manufactured arms, 1887; 1 paper, 1 photostat copy (Box 61)
        Contains serial numbers and/or Museum tag numbers for all items listed.
        Arranged by date of entry or by tag number. No index.
        The unbound inventory was compiled by C.J. Ehbets.
      - List of arms lent to Columbian Exposition (photostat, original, and typed copies), 1893 (Box 61)
      - Inventory of manufactured arms (with notations from 1929 and 1942; with serial numbers) (bound) (Box 61)
        The bound inventory contains notations of missing arms and company donations to the World War II scrap metal campaign. Internal evidence suggests that it was compiled prior to 1929.
    - Assorted sketches, lists of exhibited arms, and examples of past displays, as saved by staff members (Box 61)
    - Visitor's registries, 1934-1956 (Box 62)
      3 volumes (2 are spiral notebooks, 1 is bound)
    - Papers relating to transfer of collection of firearms and business archives to the State of Connecticut, 1957 (Box 62)
      Includes copy of invitation, newspaper clippings and event program.
  - Records of Colt Company Production, 1851-1945
    See also Business File Series 4, Production records, 1856-1928.
    - Colt Production of firearms, 1914-1945; 1 bound volume (Box 62)
      Compiled by A.L. Ulrich and R.E. Courtney in 1914. This volume is divided into 4 sections, the first of which is an overview of production prior to 1914. (Drafts of this section are located in the Company Histories File). Carbon copy reports dated February 1945 cover the three other sections; Automatics, Current Revolvers, and Obsolete Revolvers and Automatics. These reports include information such as model name, factory model letter, general description, calibers, barrel lengths, bore and groove diameters, rifling, serial numbers, and additional comments.
      Arranged by factory model letter, these reports appear to have been added to the initial production folder of 1914, by Museum Curator, C.H. Coles, and then placed in one volume.
    - Payroll Records, 1851-1936; 13 folders (Box 64)
      Lists of contractors and work completed. Occupation and political preference noted. Contractors' payroll and rent, change in pay rates, lists of employees.
      Arranged chronologically. No index.
  - Records of Colt Company Property, circa 1836-1980
    - South Meadows File, 1853-1867 (Box 62)
      South Meadows file contains documents re land purchases, circa 1853 and the following pertaining to work on the rebuilding of the factory after the fire: unbound daybook of expenditures and small leather bound volume account book (Old brick), 1866-1867. Fire took place in 1864.
    - Production Projects (Box 62A-62C)
      Contains files of production projects undertaken by Colt Industries in the period 1960-1980, including files re the establishment of manufacturing plants in Indonesia, Singapore, Korea and the Philippines, transferred during the 1981 company move to West Hartford.
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 63)
      Also newspaper clippings of early advancements and improvements. Taken from old binder in February 1944 and reworked by H. Hart.
      - 1836 February-1852 June (Box 63)
      - 1852 August-1858 April (Box 63)
      - 1858 May-1861 January (Box 63)
      - 1852-1858 (Box 63)
      - 1853-1858 (Box 63)
    - Lamar, Texas (Box 63)
      Includes correspondence to Colt's from Harry Traylor, 1942, with typed copies of deeds, and a map of the purchased area, 1856-1870.
    - Miscellaneous, 1871-1872 (Box 63)
      Includes insurance statement under Mrs. E.H. Colt's name, 1871-1872, for land on South Meadows.
      See also map and picture flat filing drawers for the following: original lease of Samuel Colt to first factory in Hartford, 1847; Samuel Colt's Lands, 1852 (2 large maps encapsulated).
  - Index to Correspondence
    Incomplete file of incoming and outgoing correspondence, 1847-1888. Cross-referenced by sender, by receiver and by subject. Prepared by L. Heffner, undated. Contains index to W.B. Franklin's diary of 1865-1867, with additional summaries of January-March, 1871 diary, which was not transferred to the State Library. Dates of correspondence covered are as follows: April-December 1847; August, October-December 1850; September, October, December 1851; January, February, April-June, October-December 1852; 1853, except August; January 1854; November 1856; August 1862, and February, March 1888.
    Arranged by date of item, or by entry, and cross-referenced throughout with name of sender, or receiver, and by subject.
    - Index to Correspondence (Item Item 99)
- Publications File, circa 1850-1980; T001481; 6.75 cubic feet
  - Advertising and Marketing Departments, circa 1850-1980
    These materials vary depending upon the target group. In selling to the general public, security and protection of the home was stressed, while endorsements from satisfied police officers were presented for possible sales to police departments. Promotional aids such as advertising cuts and displays for use by dealers were distributed by the Colt Company. Some include fold-outs, press kits and duplicate copies. All of these materials differ in size, type of paper, style of print and number of pages. For trade abroad, items were printed in foreign languages, i.e., French, Spanish, Russian and Chinese. Advertising materials from the 1960s-1970s were accessioned in the spring of 1981. These items were collected from the advertising closet at Colt's Armory. During the company's move to West Hartford, the Curators of the Museum of Connecticut History were allowed to go through and take any of the advertising materials left.
    Files are arranged chronologically by date or item, or by period of production (model of firearm). No index.
    - Firearms (Box 65)
      Includes press releases, Consumer analysis, original and printed copies of advertising lay-outs (oversize, Box 65A), promotional packets, and dealer handouts. Also, purchase orders to/from Colt's (1942; 1970). Also, a description of arms displayed in 1926 Sesqui-Centennial Celebration called Evolution of the Revolver.
    - Accessories (Box 65)
      - Historical Prints, 1943; 8 items (7 prints + 1 duplicate) (Box 65)
        Distributed by the Small Arms Division, these sets of 6 prints were quite popular and sold very well. (1943 April-1943 December 31 = 20,000 sets sold)
      - Commemorative Series of firearms, 1961; 2 folders (Box 65)
        Celebrating anniversaries of statehoods, the lives of well-known people in history, and depicting celebrated battles from a century of wars.
      - Archery Divison, 1962 (Box 65)
        Includes samples of advertisements used in various magazines.
      - Gun Oil Project, 1969-1970 (Box 65)
        With background from 1965.
      - Holsters, 1970 (Box 65)
      - Jewelry, 1970 (Box 65)
      - Security Equipment, 1970 (Box 65)
        Includes material on bomb disposal systems and handcuffs.
    - Advertisements (Box 66)
      - Advertisements from various publications, 1 folder (Box 66)
        Includes an original and photocopy of 1860 publication,
        The Knickerbocker
        , with testimonials of Colt's pistols (last 8 pages); a 1889 October full-page ad in
        Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
        (oversize, Box 65A); 1909 ad from
        Everybody's Magazine
        , p. 79
        Scribner's
        , 1917-1918 back cover.
      - Outing, 1919 April-September, volume 72, bound volume (Box 66)
    - Broadsides and Circulars, 5 folders (Box 66)
      Distributed by the Colt Company. These are published with the target group in mind: for dealers, advertising cuts and display ideas are included; for police department, specific arms are highlighted, and for the public, operation and correct use of whatever gun purchased is stressed.
    - Catalogues (Box 67)
      - 1888, paper cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1890 January, 2nd ed., c.1, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1890 January, 2nd ed., c.2, paper cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1890 January, 2nd ed., c.3, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1892 January, 3rd ed., c.1, paper cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1898 January, c.2, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1898 January, c.3, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1899 September, c.1, paper cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1902, c.2, paper cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1905, c.1, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1905, c.2, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - 1905, c.3, leather cover-bound (Box 67)
      - circa 1900 (Box 68)
      - 1903-1916, 1919-1923 (Box 68)
      - undated (Box 68)
      - Romance of a Colt (Box 68)
      - Makers of History/F. Romer Evolution of the Colt, 1926 November, c.2 (Box 68)
      - Double Action Handbook (Box 68)
      - Colt's Fire Arms Sales Manual (Box 68)
      - Colt's Police Revolver Handbook, 1913 (Box 68)
      - Colt's Police Revolver Handbook, 1924 (Box 68)
      - Colt's Police Revolver Handbook, 1925 (Box 68)
      - Colt's Police Revolver Handbook, 1943 (Box 68)
      - Colt's Police Revolver Handbook, 1943 (Box 68)
        Different edition.
    - Catalogues and Brochures (Box 69)
      Including 1887 handwritten description of Franklin Magazine Rifle, pamphlets on various automatic pistols and military sporting rifles, and export catalogue, and 1874-1881 (inclusive) annual sales booklets.
      - Colt Gun and Dundonald Gun Carriage and Ammunition Cart, 1889 (Box 69)
        See oversize.
      - Colt Gun and Dundonald Gun Carriage and Ammunition Cart, 1900 (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Colt Automatic Machine Gun (Ordnance Department), 1913 (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Browning Machine Rifle M1918 (Ordnance Department), 1918 February (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Browning Machine Rifle M1918 (Ordnance Department - War Plans Division), 1918 June (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Vicker's Machine Gun M1915, 1917 (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Vicker's Machine Gun M1915, 1918 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Cover-pirate, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Crossed pistol and revolver with world and rampant colt behind guns; grey/green cover (A-70-3rd), circa 1925 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Same cover design; grey/green cover, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Same cover design; brown cover (A-70-9th), undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Same cover design: brown cover (A-70-10th), undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in blue with blue cover, 1931 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in brown with tan cover, 1932 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in grey with grey cover, 1934 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in green with grey cover, 1935 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in red with grey cover, 1936 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in red with grey cover, 1938 (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in green with blue cover, 1941 January (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Embossed rampant colt and "Colt Firearms" in green with blue cover, 1941 July (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Colt Automatic Gun/Browning's Patent; beige outer cover, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Colt Automatic Gun/Browning's Patent; grey cover with red writing and red rampant colt, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Colt Automatic Gun/Browning's Patent; brown cover with black writing and black rampant colt, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Colt's Automatic Gun/Browning's Patent; battle scence in blues, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/Colt's Automatic Gun/Browning's Patent; battle scene in greens, undated (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/M1919 Automatic Machine Gun/Rifle/Aircraft Machine Gun - brown cover "A60" (Box 69)
      - Catalogue/M1919 Automatic Machine Gun/Rifle/Aircraft Machine Gun - brown cover "A60-R" (Box 69)
      - Handbook for Automatic Machine Gun and Aircraft Machine Gun; M1924, undated (Box 69)
      - Automatic Machine Guns and Rifles "HDF" with diagrams, c.15, 1932 (Box 69)
      - Thompson Submachine Gun, undated (Box 69)
      - Thompson Submachine Gun M1921-23, undated (Box 69)
    - Foreign Materials/Colt's (Box 69)
      - Advertisements (Box 69)
      - Catalogues, pamphlets, and handouts (Box 69)
      - Price lists (Box 69)
      - Trade letters, circa 1930 (Box 69)
    - Foreign Materials/non-Colt's (Box 70)
      - Schulhof, 1887 (Box 70)
      - M1886/Webley (Government arms) (Box 70)
      - M1889/Webley (Box 70)